Foster Grant Collection
Foster Grant Collection
1900s-1989
Foster Grant (Firm)
3.5 linear ft.
Foster Grant was an American plastics molding and manufacturing firm specializing in eyewear. Originally founded in 1919 by Sam Foster to produce ladies hair accessories, the first piece of eyewear sold in 1929 at the Woolworth in Atlantic City. Collection contains company publications and sales materials including a training binder from the 1970s containing photographs and handwritten directions on how to create an epoxy mold; and photographs of die molds, Foster Grant products from World War II and sales displays.
2651120
Biographical History
Foster Grant was an American plastics molding and manufacturing firm specializing in eyewear. Originally founded in 1919 by Sam Foster to produce ladies hair accessories, the first piece of eyewear sold in 1929 at the Woolworth in Atlantic City. In 1934, Foster Grant became the first American company to adopt injection molding. Their famous ad campaign from the 1960s, "Who's Behind Those Foster Grants," made them a household word. The original Foster Grant molding operation focused on manufacturing a variety of sunwear frames with glass. In the early 1970's Foster Grant introduced molded acrylic lenses and later developed silicone hardcoats to protect the lenses from scratching. By 1982, Foster Grant no longer manufactured glass lenses for eyewear. By the late 1980's Foster Grant began to focus on the safety and military markets. In August 1990, the Foster Grant Corporation declared bankruptcy. Almost one year later, the Technical Products Division of Foster Grant was sold to Fosta-Tek Optics, Inc., a newly-created company headed by John Morrison Jr., President and majority stockholder. Accessories Associates, Inc. purchased Foster Grant in 1996.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Foster Grant Collection contains company publications and sales materials (including a training binder from the 1970s with photographs and handwritten directions on how to create an epoxy mold), photographs of die molds, Foster Grant products from World War II and sales displays.
Corporate materials consists of Foster Grant's annual reports, the company newsletter, and items related to the company's history.
Correspondence is comprised of miscellaneous Foster Grant order forms and manufacturer letters, including those from the Mazzucchelli company as well as letters related to the Foster Grant Heart-Lung Pump between Dr. Sigmund Wesolowski, Dr. Herman Sugarman, and Robert Ward.
The Photographs consist of both personal and product related items as well as Foster Grant manufacturing machinary. Also included are 200+ photographs of die molds.
Product literature consists of manufacturer information related to Foster Grant products, including handwritten directions on how to create an epoxy mold. In addition, there are sunglass advertisements and catalogues, including their famous "Who's Behind Those Foster Grants?" campaign; advertisements and illustrations related to the Foster Grant Heart-Lung Pump, and various other product literature.
The Miscellaneous documents consist of notes belonging to Emilio Iacoboni regarding Foster Grant and various items pertaining to the Foster Grant company.
Arrangement of the Collection
Corporate materials are arranged alphabetically and chronologically within, correspondence is arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically within, photographs are arranged by subject, and product literature is arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically within.
Related Material
has numerous holdings in the areas of plastics and industrial design. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Plastics; Fost-Tek Optics, Inc.; Foster Grant (Firm) -- Archives.; Plastics industry and trade.; Sunglasses industry.; Sunglasses.; Eyeglasses.; Plastics -- Molds.; Sunglasses.; Photographs.; Promotional materials.; Training manuals.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from National Plastics Center and Museum, 11/06/2008. Originally, gift of Fosta-tek Optics, Inc.
Inventory
- Corporate materials
  - Annual reports, 1959-1973; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Binder, printed with a Foster Grant Logo on its cover (Oversize 1)
  - Buildings plans/drawings, 1933-1979; 20 drawings (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1965-1993; undated (Box 1)
  - Company history, 1974; undated; company stationery, annual meeting of stockholders booklet, company timeline and history clipping, and 3 commemorative 50 year anniversary booklets (circa 1969) (Box 1)
  - Company newsletter, Forum and Gazette, 1965-1981; 5 folders (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  - Heart-lung pump, 1950-1957; correspondence between Dr. Sigmund Wesolowski, Dr. Herman Sugarman, and Robert Ward; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1970-1989; Company order forms and manufacturer letters, including those from the Mazzucchelli company (Box 3)
- Photographs
  - Buildings, 1987; photographs and negatives of Foster Grant company (Box 3)
  - Die molds, series number unknown; 10 photographs (Box 7)
  - Die molds, incomplete series 7-287, some include an article number (example: Die Mold #245, Article #345); 99 photographs (Box 7)
  - Die molds, incomplete series 291-549, some include an article number (example: Die Mold #291, Article #335); 103 photographs (Box 8)
  - Die molds, incomplete series 554-1092, some include an article number (example: Die Mold #613, Article #834); 102 photographs (Box 9)
  - Molds, 16 photographs (Box 3)
  - Other eye glasses, ski goggles and eye shields (Box 3)
  - Other products, gas mask lenses/valves, combs, Gillette safety razor box, match box, card holder (Box 3)
  - Sunglasses, 1958-1988; photographs and negatives of displays and models; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, photographs and negatives of beach scene and typed letters (Box 3)
- Product literature
  - Combs, catalogs (Box 3)
  - Cups, circa 1961; catalogs (Box 3)
  - Heart-lung pump
    - Advertisements, circa 1953; "Uses Unlimited" bulletin and "The Graham Dial" monthly bulletin (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1950-1954; features an artist rendering and with accompanying article on "A Second Heart" (Box 4)
    - Prints and photocopies (Box 4)
    - Technical info drawings/notes, 1950-1957; undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Technical info drawings/notes (oversize), 1952; blueprints; 4 drawings (Map-case 97)
    - Miscellaneous, booklet for State Mutual Life insurance, "A Pump For Artificial Maintenance of the Circulation" booklet, two photographs of mechanical object (Box 4)
  - Manufacturer, technical information on resins, molds, machinary, and handwritten instructions on the making of a prototype expoxy mold (Box 4)
  - Sunglasses
    - Ad copy, 1951-1966; advertising schedule, media schedule, ad plan letters, articles and accompanying photographs (Box 4)
    - Advertisements, circa 1955-1965; magazine ads, photocopied newspaper ads, window display ads (Box 4)
    - Advertisements, 1960s; magazine ads (Oversize 1)
    - Catalogs, 1958-1972; features famous "Who's Behind Those Foster Grants?" ad campaign; 5 folders (Box 5)
    - Catalogs, 1973-1984; features sport and outdoor activity sunglasses; 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 10/3/1966; article from Management & Selling regarding new suntower display units (Box 6)
    - Dealer Literature, selling guides, order forms and price listings, registration cards, selling incentives, etc. (Box 6)
    - Packaging, adult and child sunglass cards (Box 6)
  - Other products
    - Advertisements, 1960-1963; Joe Foster pictured in several ads regarding plastic resins, molds, and materials that appeared in various plastics magazines (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous
  - Photograp hs/notes, 1934; 1974,; undated; handwritten notes about Sam Foster by Emilio Iacoboni and photographs of Emilio Iacobini and Sam Foster as well as unidentified factories; 2 folders (Box 6)